Jeremy Emmett

+31 62 7345813 | j.emmett@vu.nl Age: 32, Citizenship: United States

LinkedIn: www.linkedin.com/in/jeremyemmett

I'm a doctoral graduate with six years of international PhD and postdoctoral planetary/earth science research experience. My cross-disciplinary projects utilized computer modeling to interpret Martian climate history from patterned layers in the planet's polar ices, and to investigate Earth's permafrost carbon cycle. I have additional experience in varied science support and teaching roles. I have a continuing interest in projects focused on data analysis, modeling, teaching, software engineering/operations, or field/lab technical work.

Employment

Department of Earth Sciences, Vrije Universiteit Amsterdam

09/2021 - 09/2024

Postdoctoral Researcher, Supervisors: Prof. dr. Jorien Vonk & Prof. dr. Sander Houweling

Investigating the role of microbe dynamics in driving methane emission (or uptake) surface fluxes in the subarctic, using a self-developed, process-based model (*Python*). Field and lab work to measure surface gas fluxes and various biogeochemical soil properties. Python teaching assistant.

Planetary Data System Atmospheres Node, New Mexico State University

06/2020 - 07/2021

Research Engineer, Associate, Supervisor: Dr. Nancy Chanover

Migration of spacecraft instrument datafile labels from PDS3 (ASCII) to PDS4 (XML) (Python).

Department of Astronomy, New Mexico State University

08/2014 - 05/2020

Graduate Research Assistant, Advisor/Supervisor: Dr. Jim Murphy

Interpreting Martian polar ice stratigraphy as a planetary climate record, using the 'NASA Ames Mars GCM' (FORTRAN) and a self-developed long-term polar ice & dust deposition model (IDL) to predict layer production in response to climate variations. Astronomy teaching assistant.

Laboratory for Atmospheric and Space Physics

05/2013 - 07/2014

Undergraduate Research Assistant, Supervisor: Dr. Nick Schneider

Identifying optimal time windows for MAVEN spacecraft observations of Martian aurorae, using self-developed routines (*IDL*) and the 'NASA SPICE' data toolkit to visualize instrument observation geometries with respect to global magnetic field topology.

Education

New Mexico State University, Las Cruces, NM, USA

Doctor of Philosophy (PhD) and Master of Science (MS), Astronomy

Conferred: 05/2020

University of Colorado Boulder, Boulder, CO, USA

Bachelor of Arts (BA), Astronomy, with distinction (minor: mathematics) Conferred: 05/2014

Skills

- <u>Python</u>, <u>IDL</u>, FORTRAN, MATLAB
- Numerical modeling, data analysis & visualization
- Planetary/Earth science research & teaching
- Linux, MS Windows, MS Office

Publications

- *In-Preparation:* **Emmett, J.**, G. Hensgens, J. Vonk, S. Houweling, J. Weedon, and W. Lenstra. Documentation of a microbial model of methane production in subarctic active layer soils. 2024.
- **Emmett, J.**, J. Murphy, and M. Kahre. Obliquity Dependence of the Formation of the Martian Polar Layered Deposits. 2020. *Planetary and Space Science*.
- Smith, I., + 37 co-authors including **J. Emmett***. The Holy Grail: A Roadmap for Unlocking the Climate Record Stored within Mars' Polar Layered Deposits. 2020. *Planetary and Space Science*.
- Becerra, P. + 18 co-authors including **J. Emmett***. Past, Present and Future of Mars Ice Research: Conclusions and Outlook of the 7th International Conference on Mars Polar Science and Exploration. 2021. *The Planetary Science Journal*.

Grants and Honors

2019/2020 NMSU Barry Neil Rappaport Endowed Memorial Scholarship (\$1000)

05/2020

NASA Earth and Space Science Fellowship (NESSF) #NNX16AP37H (\$119,000)

09/2016 - 08/2019

New Mexico Space Grant Consortium Fellowship #NNX15A51H (\$5000)

08/2019 - 12/2019

Professional Service

Secondary Reviewer and Executive Secretary: NASA ROSES Solar System Working Program

03/2021

Reference Contacts

Prof. dr. Jorien Vonk

Vrije Universiteit Amsterdam, Dpt. of Earth Sciences, Amsterdam, Netherlands. Professor. Relationship: Primary postdoctoral supervisor j.e.vonk@vu.nl | +31 20 59 87366

Dr. Jim Murphy

New Mexico State University, Dpt. of Astronomy, Las Cruces, NM, USA. Emeritus Professor, Retired Associate Dean for Research Arts/Sciences Relationship: PhD Advisor/Supervisor murphy@nmsu.edu

Dr. Melinda Kahre

NASA/Ames Research Center, Mountain View, CA, USA. Director, Mars Climate Modeling Center Relationship: External PhD research collaborator melinda.a.kahre@nasa.gov | +1 (650) 604-3863

Dr. Nicholas Schneider

University of Colorado at Boulder,
Dpt. Of Astrophysical and Planetary Sciences
Laboratory for Atmospheric and Space Physics
Boulder, CO, USA.
Professor. MAVEN IUVS Instrument Lead.
Relationship: LASP supervisor
nick.schneider@lasp.colorado.edu
+1 (303) 492-7672

Dr. Nancy Chanover

New Mexico State University, Dpt. of Astronomy, Las Cruces, NM, USA. Professor, PI of NASA PDS Atmospheres Node | Relationship: PDS supervisor nchanove@nmsu.edu | +1 (575) 646-2567